this episode is sponsored by indeed
prime indeed prime helps software
developers simplify their job search and
land their dream job candidates get
immediate exposure to the best tech
companies with just one simple
application - indeed product companies
on Prime's exclusive platform message
candidates with salary and equity up
front
the average software developer gets five
employer contacts and an average salary
offer of $125,000 indeed Prime's 100%
free for candidates no strings attached
and when you're hired indeed prime gives
you a two thousand dollar bonus to say
thanks for using primes
but if you use the SE radio link you'll
get a five thousand dollar bonus instead
so sign up at indeed.com / se radio
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software so I come this is a bot
both I'm sitting here on skype with
Phillip Carter who is the program
manager for F sharp at Microsoft so
thanks a lot for finding the time
Phillip do you want to say a few words
about yourself introduce yourself what
you were doing and how you're related to
F sharp yes hi thanks for having me on
the show so as you said I'm a program
manager for F sharp Microsoft I work on
the visual F sharp language and tooling
team so we we work on the compiler we
work on the tooling in in Visual Studio
and we work on integration with.net
framework on the core and basically all
things net previously I'd worked on
the.net core team so one of the things
that I focus on now is getting an F
sharp to run really really smoothly and
on that core so that we can have
official cross-platform support for F
sharp on net so can you say if Hubert's
about what f sharp actually is so f
sharp is a functional first
multi-paradigm programming language it's
kind of a lot of words but basically
it's it's a general-purpose programming
language that you can effectively do
anything you really want to with however
we kind of put this skew on doing things
in a functional way kind of adhering the
functional programming concepts such as
immutability higher-order functions
you know this manipulation data
wrangling all that kind of stuff
every language is somehow influenced by
other languages and there is a whole
tree of history of languages I guess
which programming languages was F sharp
influenced by so F sharp is influenced
by a number of images I guess the most
core language that it's probably
influenced from would be ml or standard
ml which is kind of a this research
programming language
that is oriented around the
hindley-milner type system there have
been multiple derivatives of that such
as Oh camel and Haskell and they're kind
of all in this family of languages and
f-sharp is another one of these
derivative and now languages that's kind
of a peer language with Haskell and oh
camel and so that there are pieces of
Haskell and Oh camel that have kind of
made its way into f-sharp just as an
influential thing some bits from other
languages have made it in as well and
then F sharp on the other side has
actually influenced a lot of what's gone
on with C sharp and Visual Basic with
some of its features that are kind of
pioneered relatively early on when you
say it has been influenced by the ML and
Haskell in which family is that the
features or rather the syntax that that
it took from those languages it's it's
kind of both so the syntax is definitely
the more obvious one not necessarily
from Haskell but if you were to look at
Oh camel code for example it looks
really really similar to f-sharp in fact
they're the ones that are the most
similar in fact they share a lot of the
same keywords and you could you could
write code and Oh camel f-sharp and it's
generally speaking not too difficult to
port it to one one of the other I mean
there's some quirks with the language
and things like that you must have
worked out but then there are some of
the features like having a more powerful
type system having type inference in the
language is something that F sharp was
certainly influenced by from those other
languages in addition to ml that's kind
of one of the core things of that family
of languages is the type system because
it's what I'd mentioned is the
hindley-milner type system which is this
this way of inferring types from things
and it's this algorithm that was derived
by these computer scientists and believe
it was the late 70s or the early 80s
where they effectively came up with an
efficient way to understand the types of
things at compile time so you wouldn't
have to explicitly annotate every single
type if you wanted to use it as that
particular type and that's I think kind
of a central thing that influenced a
sharp also you said that languages like
C sharp are influenced by F sharp so
what are some features that C sharp
from f-sharp I want to be careful when I
say took because it's more of an
influential things so with f-sharp an
example is a language level asynchronous
programming also known as async
workflows in F sharp these were
introduced before language level async
made it into c-sharp and although they
have different concepts for how
asynchronous code is handled F sharp was
kind of a pioneer in that you know it
was hey you know can we make
asynchronous programming a language
construct and have syntax around that
and will people like it and the answer
was well yes people liked it a lot and
so c-sharp was able to say okay well you
know people really do like this thing so
you know what's a way that we can have a
language level asynchronous code in a
way that that feels natural to c-sharp
and that's that's kind of that that sort
of influence that we had there some
recent things that are coming along now
with c-sharp seven notably tuples and
well I think it's just tuples now with
and we're going to have pattern matching
coming along pretty soon and these are
things that are kind of also very
foundational pieces of F sharp that
people love using and so C sharp said
okay well you know there's there's a
particular style of programming
oftentimes working with data that people
love these language constructs for and
so they can look at it and say okay well
this is how they do match expression
this is how tuples are deconstructed
this is how tuples are returned from
functions and we're seeing that same
sort of influence happening right now in
things that are being actively developed
with c-sharp and also with visual basics
it also has the asynchronous programming
that's there's a prototype for Visual
Basic actually right now that I think
with a preview version of Visual Studio
you can use pattern matching and things
like that so those are sort of the areas
where it's been influential right now
that's Jeff's I've only worked on that
on that platform or and it also create
native code or are there any other
platforms that are supported right now
it is only dotnet when I say only dot
that actually means a couple different
things first of all when you talk about
concrete implementations it means the
don''t framework which is the runtime
and drivers collector that have existed
in dotnet for a very long time
we have dotnet core which is a
cross-platform
and drivers collector that works on lots
of different Linux distributions and Mac
and it also runs on that although in an
alpha state right now we're working
towards a 1.0 for F sharp on Donna core
then it also runs on mono which is
another implementation of dotnet that's
entirely cross-platform and so there's
kind of these these three core places
that it will run however outside of
those there there isn't really any
support and there is no support that I
know of for native F sharp
we do have a native compilation tool
chain that we are looking to support F
sharp with however because that's still
very very early technology there are
quite a few areas where F sharp will
just simply not work on that right now
but we anticipate being able to generate
native code from F sharp with the done
at native tool chain I'd say within the
next year or two are you planning to do
an implementation on the JVM no we
certainly there are quite a few
languages so you mentioned okay I'm all
yourself and you know there is garland
in the in the Java world and that's
quite huge
there is Haskell and that's also gaining
some traction why not just thought one
of those languages yeah that's that's
actually a pretty good question because
those are awesome languages right you
know Scala has amazing features like you
know personally I'm a huge fan of higher
kind of types in Scala and type classes
in Haskell and you know it'd be it would
be awesome to have that working you know
actually Haskell for a time did have a
dotnet implementation I just don't think
it was ever really actively maintained
but I think you know because I wasn't
involved in the creation in the language
I can't really specifically say why it
why not just part one of them but to be
frank it's just really cool creating
programming languages and you know you
have that level of control of saying you
know oh well there are these little
quirks with this one language that I
just don't really like you know is there
a way that we can you know flip those
around or you know do what we think
makes sense in this context and I would
imagine would be one of the motivations
there so it's not about creating
functional programming languages for
the.net platform and using the the
specifics of that platform that's not
the reason why
f-sharp was created
well so we did absolutely want to have a
functional programming language on
the.net platform
I just think taking an existing
functional programming language that was
just not one of the reasons that was
taken for I think well you know I I
guess it's just really speculation at
this on my own because I wasn't involved
trading the language but there are some
trade-offs that are made in certain
languages but may not necessarily have
been appropriate for dotnet at least not
at the time the SR was created so you
already spoke about typing appearance
and and actually I think that's quite a
great feature so can you say a few words
about that as far as I understand it
basically means that you don't have to
decay in any types anymore yeah in a way
so type inference is well as you said
you don't you don't really have to
declare types the compiler is able to
figure out what things are now there are
some limitations to that usually when
you're attempting to use a variable that
you know you say you have a parameter to
a function and you did not annotate the
type that is an option you can annotate
types which say you didn't and then you
used it in some way that might be
ambiguous right you know the particular
operation that you're performing on it
might be valid for more than just one
type at that point the compiler will say
hey I need you to tell me specifically
which one this is because you know out
of this vast array of functionality that
could be performed on a type there
happens to be some ambiguity going on
and so that's usually where the
limitations are that's a very few and
far between things I think you'll find
if you were to write a large solution in
f-sharp you know a lot of code say you
know well over a thousand lines of code
very very little of that would ever
include annotated types and so that buys
you a lot of things because well first
of all it's less code and less code
means less bugs because there's just
less stuff that could possibly go wrong
the second thing that buys you is less
poetic to call cognitive overload you
know reading code is always one of those
things that takes a lot longer than
writing it well it oftentimes takes a
lot longer like if you if you're reading
a large file and you've never seen it
before
things like type annotations everywhere
just kind of get in the way of you
trying to understand what the code
is actually trying to do and so this is
a huge benefit there when you're looking
at a code base that you may not really
fully understand yet then another really
awesome benefit type inference has is
you can write code you see you write a
function and take some parameters you do
some operations on it and then you
return a value you may have thought in
your head as you were writing it these
are operations that are happening on a
very specific type and you just chose
not to annotate it because it was less
stuff for you to type into the computer
but then the compiler may have actually
said ah but what you've done here is
actually a little bit more generic and
so you can you can sometimes
inadvertently write more generic code
because the compiler says oh well this
routine that you've written here is
valid for more than just one type and so
then you can reuse that in more places
and so that code reuse thing is kind of
one of those I like to call it
ambient code reuse because it's just as
you're writing the code you'll notice
that you can use your functions in more
places than you may have thought you
could have and that's because the
compiler infers the types for you you're
able to reap that benefit do you have
any idea why where there are not a lot
more languages that use these this
concept I think one of the answers is
that it's really hard the type inference
algorithm that we use it's it's based
off of something that's very established
but you know it's still an exceptionally
challenging thing to get right
not just from a correctness standpoint
but from an efficiency standpoint
because this is all at compile time
right none of this is happening at
runtime if you don't have a good
implementation then your compile times
just explode basically you know a great
example of this actually is something
that recently came up with Swift so
Swift is an amazing programming language
that Apple has come out with that I
really love using and I encourage
everybody who's a fan of programming
languages to go out there just try it
out because it's really great but they
they had a bug where someone was writing
a unit test and he had been using type
inference and he just declared a
dictionary that was kind of hard coded
for a unit test so that he could compare
it with the result of whatever he was
testing and it took 12 hours to compile
because it happened too
go down a path where the Swift compiler
just and ended up in like this really
really inefficient pathway of trying to
infer what type this this hard-coded
dictionary actually was and so things
like that are really really challenging
and I just think it's it's it's less
common because it's such a difficult
problem to tackle that many many
languages just choose not to tackle it
at least that's that's my perception I
found an interesting that you said that
it's easier to read code that uses type
inference because actually I would think
that if you annotate a parameter or
variable with some type it's actually
sort of a documentation because what
you're saying is this should really be
this type so what do you think about
that do you think that's that's a valid
argument or would you say that generally
speaking type interferences is actually
but superior in that regard also I
definitely view it on a spectrum sort of
thing I think that in the large when you
have a big file or you know lots of
files and just tons of things going on
there if every single thing has an
annotated type you know it's my belief
in my sort of experience with that sort
of stuff is a lot of that just kind of
ends up being noise right you know if I
if I were to call some library function
that got a string from an HTTP GET then
I would know that it's just it's a
string because that's just what the data
is and so the fact that the result is
annotated with the type string isn't
necessarily going to be relevant
information for me if I just want to
find out what's going on there however
sometimes it definitely is a good way to
sort of document exactly what this thing
should be doing and so I we I just kind
of view it as a case by case basis where
if it makes sense if you think that you
know hey if someone's reading this code
and they may not necessarily understand
that this variable is supposed to be a
string then annotating it with a string
makes perfect sense to me or you know if
you're declaring a class and f-sharp for
example and in the constructor you're
taking in say like something called IP
address and port IP address a lot of
people might use that as a string
representation but if the particular API
that you are using
to register the IP address didn't take
it as a string it took it as I don't
know it's something else then annotating
it as that something else is definitely
helpful because it's not really a kind
of a common way that that people might
represent that and so I think I might
even I might even say that for common
cases where you bind results to bear to
values or or you have parameters as
functions or that sort of stuff and if
it's a very common way that you would
represent something then type inference
on not needing to annotate types is a
benefit but if it's something where it's
not necessarily the most obvious thing
and type annotation it is entirely
possible for you to do and so you could
go ahead and annotate it and then it's
very obvious what needs to happen and so
there's also a bit of an analogue here
in F sharp there's also something called
type declaration there are these files
that usually sit alongside your source
files so say you have your you know
source FS which is contains your code
for doing something you could also
create a file called source FSI which is
where all of your type declarations go
so you could say okay well I have this
module called food and inside the food
module I have these three functions and
then these three functions all I have is
a type signature where I say well this
is the name this is the input and it's
typed this is another input in its type
this is the results and its type and
then you could put you know any kind of
documentation there and you can you can
add labels to the types to give the
names and that sort of stuff and so
that's a sort of an effective way to
document code from an API level
perspective because then you can point
people to FSI file and you can say oh
well you don't have to be bothered to
you know if all you care about is
consuming this particular function then
you don't have to look through the
potentially big source file that
contains you know a whole bunch of logic
in there you might just want to know
okay what are the input types what are
the output types and in that case the
type declaration file like that is
incredibly helpful so F sharp kind of
has because it has you know it's its
type inference but you can come you can
declare types if you think that you need
them or if you have to use them they're
our type declaration files that you can
use to make things a bit more clear it's
there are a lot of tools in your tool
basically you're not opted into just one
specific way of doing things and I think
that that's something that sets a sharp
apart from many other languages because
you can choose which tool fits what
you're trying to do the most instead of
having to use one particular way that
having to use one particular way thing
is something that is more common with
most other languages do you have any
idea how often those three ways like
either type interference or declaring
types in line or having these these
separated files how often those three
features are used of the language so I
would say that's having no type
declarations is the most common thing
most F sharp code will not have it
mainly because it doesn't really need it
and usually I mean if it's good F sharp
code usually it's very obvious what's
what's happening and so then it's not
really needed but in the cases where you
need to disambiguate or the cases where
what you're doing may not necessarily be
obvious that's you know maybe 1% of the
time maybe 2% of the time kind of
depending on what's going on then you'll
have those sort of inline type
declarations or annotating those types
inline and then the type declaration
files those are common for those are
very common from API developers so like
with F sharp core which are the core
libraries that we have that have a whole
bunch of whole bunch of functions on
various types and extra types declared
that's where all of our asynchronous
programming is defined and all that kind
of stuff for every single file we also
have a corresponding declaration file
that has all the declared types for and
that's actually where we put our API
documentation because in Visual Studio
if you hit say f12 and then you go to
definition it actually takes you to that
file and then you can see you know hey
this is the API code comments that we
have in there and then underneath those
code comments you can see the type that
the compiler looks at when you're trying
to use this particular function we
already spoke about a zone blocks and as
Ramona's programming and how that
actually influenced C shop so that seems
to be another very important feature of
F sharp can you say a few words
about that how that concept works
asynchronous programming with f-sharp is
is kind of born out of a number of
problems
first of all asynchronous programming is
a difficult thing right you know the the
context in which something is executing
can be different than the context in
which your normal code might be
executing and sort of reasoning about
that and kind of thinking about what
what's going on in this context versus
that context how do I communicate you
know how do I take multiple asynchronous
contexts and have them talk to one
another
reliably that's a very difficult problem
to solve and traditionally the ways that
you would try to solve that would be
with callbacks and you know there's a
the infamous saying and nodejs
with callback hell where you have this
this triangle of doom of just all these
nested functions and you know it's not
really clear what's going to be executed
and when that's sort of a problem that's
been around for quite a long time and so
f sharp is not the first language to
have language level asynchronous
programming into it with these async
blocks but it is one of the first ones
to in my opinion adopt it in a way
that's very easy to understand so the
way that it does it is it utilizes what
are known as computation expressions and
F sharp which are sort of these ways of
being able to deal with types and what
we call elevated types so an elevated
type might be an optional an option of T
or you know if you're familiar with the
C sharp and Visual Basic world the
representation of a background task is a
task of T and then you know the T inside
of that is the thing that you care about
but you know the stuff that's going on a
synchronously you have a handle to that
with this task well that is an elevated
type compared to the T and you need some
way to do you know sort of package that
up into that task you need to unpack it
when it's appropriate and you know that
can also be a challenge and so
computation expressions are these
general approach to being able to do
that and so we've taken that general
approach and then honed in on a very
specific way so we say okay how can we
represent stuff that is happening in an
asynchronous context as an elevated type
and then how
can we use the this computation
expression syntax to make it really easy
to work with and so they're known as
async blocks where you just you have a
function in this case you would say you
know let my function async is equal to
and then you use this just this keyword
called async and then there's these
brackets inside of it and then inside of
that there's a few special key words so
the way that you would bind the result
of something to to a name in normal F
sharp is you know you say let X equal to
you know whatever the result is but in
this case if you say let's and then
exclamation mark X is equal to the
result then that's a way of saying oh
well in the context of this asynchronous
block assign the result of whatever
asynchronous thing is happening to X but
only after it's actually finished you
can utilize that to sort of just call
this asynchronous stuff inside of an
async block really easily and then the
thing that you get when you call an
async function that uses an async block
is what's known as an async of T and
that's actually a specification of a
work to be done asynchronously instead
of work that's already happening
asynchronously a way that I like to
reason about it is say I needed you to
go do something for me
in a traditional world I might tell you
immediately what what you what you need
to do and then you go off and do it and
then you just come back and you give me
whatever I need and then and then I'm
happy in the F sharp way of doing this
things instead of me immediately telling
you what you need to go do I would then
write down a specification of what you
need to do and that specification might
involve multiple different things that
you need to go maybe need to go this
store and then this store do something
with the things that you got from the
store all that kind of stuff and I would
write that down as a specification and
then explicitly hand you the
specification to perform that work
rather than telling you directly each
thing that you have to do and that's
sort of the model that we have for
basing blocks where we can say you know
when you call an asynchronous function
that is defined by an async block you
get a specification of the work that
happens in the background and then you
can choose to start that work in a way
that is most appropriate for you do you
start it on the main thread and then and
then await its results do you start it
you know do you queue it up to run on
the thread pool and then and then go do
something else do you turn it into a
different type like a task of tea and
then pass it into some c-sharp code or
some VB code there's a lot of
flexibility there where once you have
that asynchronous workflow that that
you've defined there you can then do
with it what you will and so that's that
those are kind of the pieces of what
async blocks are in a chart is that
something that is specific to a shop or
are there other languages that do
similar things see I I never actually
used it in Haskell but Haskell does have
language level async with some of their
monadic do notation and it might also
kind of do the same thing so there's
kind of two models here where there's
the hot task model or the cold task
model with a hot task model is that by
invoking an asynchronous function
there's a side-effect where something is
started in the background and then the
cold task is saying and broking it gives
you a state machine and then that state
machine you can do with it what you will
to then start that background task I
actually don't know what model they use
but I wouldn't be surprised if it was
fairly similar to what we have these
Hazzard blocks is that something that
you can use in any other internet
language or is it specific to f-sharp
only so in this case it is specific to
f-sharp
you cannot use async blocks in any other
dominant language and be model of
asynchronous programming in C sharp and
Visual Basic where they do have async
keywords for methods it is a different
model so I'd mentioned the hot task
which is called task model where in
f-sharp
invoking the function doesn't start that
background task you have to actually
explicitly start it in c-sharp in Visual
Basic invoking the method has a side
effect of also starting a background
task and so the two types task of T in
the c-sharp and visual basic world and a
sinc of T in the f-sharp world aren't
completely compatible with one another
so that there are some utility functions
in f-sharp or in in our core libraries
where you can convert an async of T into
a task of T and you can convert a task
of T into an async of T but because they
are these different models you deem you
do need to have those conversion
functions and
okay I see so there is some
compatibility layer there so that you
can actually use the ideas in the other
language was to another feature that I
found interesting is that F shop has
support for unit of measures like meters
and kilometers and it grams and stuff
like that but what's the reason for
introducing that and how is it useful so
units of measure these are one of my
personal favorite features of F sharp so
there there's kind of this problem with
integers and floats and doubles and that
sort of thing where the numeric value
itself kind of has a contextual meaning
you know the number 12 might be a
meaningful number in some contexts or it
just might be the number 12 and a
totally useless thing but most
programming languages they will usually
have some kind of API of some language
that you have to use where like an
integer is a value that you have to pass
in or a float is a value that you have
to pass in and oftentimes it's it's not
really clear what what the valid ranges
you know something maybe it throws an
exception if it's not in a particular
range or you know say I was writing a
function an API that took in the
latitude and longitude and you passed in
the latitude and longitude value that
were not valid for the planet Earth well
the function will probably fail in that
case but there may not have been a way
for you to necessarily know that as a
consumer of that API you know passing in
5000 as the latitude for you know a
point in Earth is totally valid as far
as the compiler is concerned because
it's an integer or say you're doing
something that's time-sensitive
and so seconds are measured from zero to
60 or you know 0 to 59 if you passed in
a value that was higher than than 59 or
a value that was lower than zero in most
languages that's perfectly acceptable
but in F sharp you can have a bit more
control over that because you can say oh
well this integer right here is a minute
and so when you say this is a minute
then if you tried to pass in the value
12 to a function it would fail because
it would say you passed in an integer
but I don't know what that integer
actually was you know that integer could
be anything at all you need to actually
tell me is this a minute is this a
second or something like that
and it's a way that you know at compile
time you can say oh well this this value
is context-sensitive and I'm going to
apply the proper context as I consume
the API which uses these numeric values
as inputs and that's a powerful thing
because you could have a function say
add minutes that takes in the current
time in minutes and then some minutes to
add and then in f-sharp you could
declare those types in line or with a
type declaration file as a unit of
measure for minute that you may have to
find somewhere else and so then
consumers of that would have to pass in
explicit integers that are minutes if
they were passing just regular integers
or integers that were seconds or
anything other than minutes then the
compiler would come back and say you
didn't pass the correct thing there and
that's incredibly helpful for any kind
of things where you have numeric
information that is more than just a
number like it actually has meaning and
can you also define that you may only
pass in an integer of a certain range as
your associate with the longitude there
isn't really support for this general
purpose kind of thing for you know
defining say in this case a function
which determines whether an input of a
particular type is valid and embedding
that into the unit of measure that
itself is not possible but what is
possible is eliminating you from just
passing in a number period yeah your
number needs to be a specific type of
number and so that's something that's
helpful because if you if the number
itself is of type minute then you as the
programmer can say oh well because this
is a minute it probably does have to
fall into a particular range also F shop
has some features around ESL's
domain-specific languages so how does
that work how would you create a DSL in
F sharp so DSL is an F sharp it's a very
common way dealer to to use F sharp
there's not really you know this
language level specific for dsls kind of
feature in F sharp however there are
some really useful things for writing a
DSL that are that are usually related to
the type system well I guess I should
back up for a minute it's not necessary
that ADSL is some sort of feature of
f-sharp that you can have it's really
that how you define a DSL is how you
define your parser and so f-sharp has
strengths for parsing things that will
be very beneficial for creating a DSL I
think that that's kind of a core problem
is is when you say you know I want to
create a DSL for my language what you're
actually really saying is I want to
define a parser for some input and that
parser needs to be capable of handling
all forms of that input it needs to be
able to handle it in a very correct way
and so there are a number of sort of
tools in your toolkit there your first
one would be I would say FP parsec which
is a third-party library which is very
similar to the parsec library in Haskell
which has a lot of built-in types that
are beneficial for really really common
component to the DSL that you might use
it's got flex and built-in parsing
techniques so you could just pass in a
type declaration and a string and it's
able to validate it based on that but
then outside of third-party libraries
the type system itself there f-sharp is
capable of doing a lot of things so for
example active patterns is a feature of
F shark which allows you to expand
pattern matching in F sharp kind of as a
backplate for pattern matching if people
are not familiar with how to matching
you can imagine a super powered switch
statement where you can say oh well
here's an input that's of this type and
then in all these different cases where
it could be this type or it could be
this auto type or you know it could have
this you know maybe maybe it's a tuple
type and so you know maybe one of them
is this type and one of them is this
other type or one maybe one is empty or
maybe one is not there are all these
different ways that something could be
passed into something that's valid and
so pattern matching is a really nice way
of having on the language and F sharp
has that but then you can extend that
with what are known as active patterns
which are a way of associating a pattern
with some functionality so really basic
way that you could do it is you could
say oh well here's a string and we want
to check the case where the string
contains at a particular substring well
then you could say well you could define
and then active
pattern that is able to take an input
string and then tell you whether or not
it contains a substring and then it
creates an optional type which then you
could use in pattern matching where you
would it would automatically go to the
case in your pattern matching expression
of when it matched that particular
string or it would immediately fall
through to an error case that you would
have to find and it would just
short-circuit down to the error case and
so there's this sort of built-in
language support for you know matching a
case where it works and then
short-circuit failure to the case where
it's supposed to fail is really nice
because well first of all it's a
powerful constructs second of all it's
not much code so you can define that
kind of parsing logic really concisely
and it just it plays into the type
system and so if you're able to leverage
the type system even further then you
could say well this function which does
this sort of advanced pattern matching
sort of thing ultimately returns this
specific type and then you can let type
inference sort of generalize that out if
it needs to and you could leverage that
in other places so you wouldn't need to
copy that code necessarily and then the
type system for F sharp itself just for
defining record types and discriminated
unions which are known as algebraic data
types which are these recursive types
where you know a type could also be
composed of other types that is also
composed of so like say you wanted to
represent a binary search tree binary
search trees are recursive types where
you either have an empty tree or you
have a node and then that node could
have two sub trees and then those sub
trees themselves are defined in terms of
your your recursive type that you have
themselves so they those two sub trees
are also a case of either an empty tree
or node with two sub trees and because
the type system supports that you can
very concisely represent sometimes that
more advanced type information in a way
that the compiler also understands that
sounds pretty powerful given all these
features and and how powerful def
shabbos is it meant to be a
general-purpose language or is it
something that you envision to be used
in specific use cases what is the
typical F sharp program are trying to do
with the language so I would say it is
definitely a general-purpose language
things like object orientation are fully
supported and F sharp you can create
classes interfaces abstract classes you
know all you can organize your code in
all those different ways you can use F
sharp for building user interfaces for
example xamarin you can build ios and
android apps with xamarin in F sharp you
can actually do it with simran forms you
know it's it's excellent for building
web services for example because
oftentimes you you have some some HTTP
function you know something that maybe
sits on a controller or something like
that well that can conceptually be
modeled as a function really you know
there's an input you know the input is
some HTTP and the output is some HTTP
and so that's also kind of a natural fit
for up there so it is general-purpose
now should it be a language that you
should do everything in not necessarily
and I think that the same applies to
bass to pretty much any language you
know including VB and NC sharp these are
very different languages you know the VB
and c-sharp tend to be imperative and
object-oriented first with some
functional features where f-sharp is
functional first with some imperative
and object-oriented features it just
really depends on the problem that
you're trying to solve right if you have
a system where a certain component of it
just really makes sense to be imperative
and you should write imperative code in
a language that is really easy for you
to write it and like Visual Basic or C
sharp if you have some stuff that is is
really just you know problems that you
need to solve that are functional in
nature that are you know that the vast
majority of is functionality then F
sharp is a fantastic choice and you know
when I say is functionality that that
can mean basically anything that can
mean you're writing a DSL you could
write web services maybe you're doing
some sort of mathematical thing maybe
you're not maybe you're just doing
general text processing maybe it's just
a rule engine for just some business
programming you have a whole bunch of
different rules that define how things
need to talk to one another you know
that's all functionality that can be
written in F sharp
there's not really a limit there and so
there are a lot of different people that
is f sharp for different things so for
example jet comm is a competitor to
Amazon in fact one of the primary
competitors to Amazon where they have
something like 700 plus micro-services
written entirely in F sharp o stood on a
juror that define all of the rules for
how things work with their inventory
management with displaying stuff on the
website with displaying what pages are
dynamic price changing instrumentation
of all of that stuff check out you know
basically every single component of the
website is to find you know in some way
as a micro service written in F sharp
there's another startup in the Silicon
Valley area called tackiest that does
work in the energy industry and there
are a lot of things like you know
analytical dashboards needing to collect
information from all these different
devices and sort of understand that
information and kind of organize it in a
way that people can make sense out of
all of that is also written in that
sharp you know there there's also
financial groups in New York City that
that write finance code in F sharp
that's it's a wide variety of things
that you can do and so that's why we we
definitely do like to emphasize that it
is a general-purpose programming
language that you can use for just about
anything it's just a matter of you know
if it makes sense for you to use it then
and it's a good idea to use it
interesting because I mean my impression
so far was that the rise of functional
programming and that everybody's
interested in is primarily due to the
different way of doing parallel
programming so would you agree because
from what you said it just seems like
it's really a broad variety of things
that are implemented using F sharp so
it's not specific to just you know
parallel algorithms or things like that
I think things like parallel programming
and asynchrony and all that kind of
stuff there are some problems there that
functional programming in general is
very very good at solving and I think
especially with the rise of cloud
computing and a tendency to break up
monolithic services into micro services
and be more concurrent have things that
are distributed across different
machines perhaps even different clusters
of machines you basically end up in a
scenario where correctness is what
matters because when you have in for
traveling safe from one machine to
another you know how fast something
could be implemented on a particular CPU
if these values in this array are loaded
in this particular cache line in this
particular cache level and hit this
register at this time you know that
low-level stuff right there although
it's really important becomes less of a
priority when you're building something
like say an insurance marketplace
because that insurance marketplace
you're going to have to collect all
kinds of information from all over the
world and save it in all these different
places and have all these different
backup strategies and things like that
and so when you're dealing with
information coming in and going into
various places at different times and
you know it's not this synchronous thing
it might be happening in parallel it
might be just concurrent in general then
you care about things like immutability
by default and that things don't change
on you when you don't expect them to
change and you care about functionality
where there's no side-effects
it's just input and output and
organizing things that way and I think
people are more interested in functional
programming in general because of that
because their problems have effectively
risen to that level where functional
programming makes a lot of sense for
them and so f sharp is a way that you
can do that on net and there's amazing
tooling that you can use for that as
well like you can you can use Visual
Studio and you have a great ide
to kind of support you in solving those
problems with F sharp and so I think
there's a bit of an impact that
functional programming in general is
having on the industry right now and I
see it on the rise and I think a lot of
people do as well where interest is a
lot higher people are starting to
rewrite things to be more functional
because that's just kind of where
problems in general seem to be going
let's talk about a completely different
subject for a minute who is actually
developing F sharp is it just Microsoft
or what kind of organization is behind
that language um so f sharp is it's in
an interesting place
so f sharp itself the you know the
concept F sharp is not Microsoft owned
it's it's an F sharp organization that
that effectively I guess you could say
owns that sharp now Microsoft owns an
implementation of F sharp that we call
visual F sharp and this is the language
and compiler
Toulon that lives in Visual Studio and
that we have with Microsoft to anundson
although that kind of came out of
Microsoft it is a free and open-source
language that is very actively developed
on by open source contributors in fact
just to list off some recent things that
have happened one of the community
members Stephane Fortman he's been
working very heavily on changing error
messages and making them a lot better we
had another community member will I
forget his last name but he was another
community member who implemented direct
representation of the record type in F
sharp that's a really really big
challenging change to the language that
not many people would normally do in an
open-source world like oftentimes it's
usually some primary people that work in
source say language or tooling and then
there are some contributors that usually
it's kind of Lander stuff we have
community members doing really hard
stuff when doing really important stuff
with the language and they're also in
fact even driving the design of the
language so our design process is done
entirely on github entirely open-source
we create an RFC and we say hey this is
a proposal to change language or to add
a new feature or to do whatever we think
is appropriate for language and then we
open it up to the community and we say
we value your input and sometimes those
rfcs are created by community members
sometimes they're almost entirely driven
by community members and you know by the
time we at Microsoft even get around to
thinking about how we might implement
something a community member has already
made a pull request with their
implementation and then we can say oh
awesome well now we can review this and
you know talk about it for a few months
and work it out kind of work in little
details but it's a really really
fantastic way that it's that it's all
sort of organized and so there's an
f-sharp software foundation that's you
know that they have a Board of Trustees
they kind of drive the organization
itself they organize things like talks
they help with visibility and outreach
of the language and then Microsoft does
some of that itself and then Microsoft
we work very heavily on the language
itself but we also spend significant
time on the tooling and making sure that
the language runs smoothly and all of
the changes to the dawnette platform
that we create as well so that as the
dotnet platform involves the f-sharp
language can also kind of evolve on top
of it and never get
behind and there's kind of that that
sort of working relationship that we
have going on
yeah I'm sense sounds pretty great and I
guess it's just another example of how
Microsoft is using the open-source model
these days so you you said that there is
an open-source compiler
how is it different from what is
included in virtual studio and the the
visual F shop that you were talking
about the current model in which ways
are developed is so there are two
compilers as you said there's the the
open source one and the visual F sharp
compiler all current development today
happens in the open source visual F
sharp compiler and then changes that are
made there are typically back ported
into the open version and so the open
version is maintained for a few
different reasons mainly because
basically if there are any different
priorities that the community might have
or that the organization might have from
Microsoft and they say well you know 99%
of what you're doing is great but this
one little thing we think we want to do
it this way they're enabled to do that
with the open source version of the
compiler and although there's not really
much of a difference between the open F
sharp and visual F sharp actually really
the only differences these days or that
visual F sharp has a little bit more
features in it at a point in time
because just active development is
happening there but it enables the
community it empowers them to have an
open version of the language that they
can work with and organize around and
that's sort of how we have the open
compiler and the visual F sharp compiler
and so it's it's a bit interesting to
call it the open compiler because they
are both open and they are both open
source that wasn't necessarily true in
the past when visual f sharp was closed
source but visual f sharp was actually
one of the first things that Microsoft
began open sourcing and doing open
source before because there was already
this open edition of everything it was
really easy to just say oh well no it
works over there so we'll just do it
here and you know kind of in typical F
sharp fashion we pioneered in a way and
a lot of that is sort of following suit
and now you know almost all major
activity in the.net ecosystem is
happening open source on github and it's
open development as well so you know the
model that we have where community
members can make really big
changes and really empowering changes
they can do that across all dotnet now
and that's just better for everybody as
so so I could actually do a pull request
on on the visual deaf shop compiler oh
absolutely
then there's nothing stopping you from
doing it in fact if you were to go there
right now you'll probably find I don't
remember what the number was but there's
pages of pull requests open right now
and they're all under review sometimes
they're under review for a long time
because the change is a really really
challenging one and it requires months
of feedback and that sort of stuff to
get it right but you could absolutely do
it right now we merge a couple of them
every single day and any new stuff that
we do with the tooling on Microsoft side
we just create a spool request to and
the community members go in there and
engage and sometimes they actually
notice things that we did wrong and they
say oh well why is it this way and then
we say oh yeah well we didn't really
think of that and it's a really cool
relationship that we had that yeah it's
that's definitely the powerful point
sauce so what is the license for visual
f-sharp I mean the the open-source
license that you're using apache license
it's okay so it's really it's one of
those liberal if freest and free beer
license else I guess oh yes yeah
you can take this language off of you
can do anything you want you could fork
it you could make your own version of F
sharp that is totally different no
problem there so long as you just
attribute as required then it's all good
to go and in fact some people even do
that they have their own Forks of F
sharp where they might have a particular
feature that they like and they use that
you can do effectively what you want
here so what would be the easiest way to
get started with F sharp development so
the easiest way to get started with F
sharp you can go to F sharp Dada work
there's a lot of resources here there's
a little learn tab there and so you can
learn about language F sharp kind of
various resources for learning you know
there's a lot of blogs a lot of guides
various places documentation like
there's our Microsoft Visual F sharp
documentation all of this is listed on
this website here with all the different
ways that you could learn it and then
there's ways that you can try it out
like the try F sharp interactive
environment in your browser and there's
of course Visual Studio so if you
download visual
studio and then under additional
components you select Israel F sharp you
can get F sharp in your development
environment and then you can just start
hacking on the language there are a
number of books as well such as F sharp
for C sharp developers real world
functional programming functional
programming using F sharp a number of
number of these that are available on
Amazon and all of this stuff is listed
on the F sharp torque website and so I
would say if you were to go to the
website you would probably get all of
the information that you would need to
get going with using that sharp today
any other things that you want to
mention any other any questions so that
didn't really ask you I guess I would
just encourage people to especially if
you've never looked at functional
programming before and you've always you
may have heard about it maybe you
haven't and you've said oh well you know
I kind of wonder what that is you know
dip your toes into functional
programming a little bit you know try
f-chart try Scala
Hostel Oh camel try all these different
languages and just you know if anything
it can help you become a better
programmer because it'll get you to
think about things in a little different
way and I encourage people to get
started with functional programming and
you know if f-sharp is the language that
that you choose to learn cultural
programming then I'll be even happier
I totally agree I think it's really
important to turn on functional
programming not just because it's a hype
right now but because as you said to
just become a better programmer also
should stay with with imperative
languages so thanks a lot thanks a lot
for taking the time and being on the
show and yeah have a lot of success with
F help yeah and thank you so much for
having me this is splendid
[Music]
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]